Guide to the Gerald W. Williams Lantern Slides Collection circa 1900s-1930s
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Gerald W. Williams Lantern Slides Collection
circa 1900s-1930s
Williams, Gerald W.
P 319
0.30 cubic feet, including 184 lantern slides 3 boxes
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Gerald W. Williams Lantern Slides Collection consists of lantern slides assembled and acquired by Williams in the course of his work as a Forest Service sociologist and historian and due to his avocational interest in the history of forestry and the Pacific Northwest region. The slides depict forests and forest operations; landscapes and scenery; and birds, wildlife, and plants. The collection includes advertisements for local businesses in the McKenzie River area. Gerald Williams worked for the U.S. Forest Service from 1979 to 2005 as a sociologist (1979-1998) and historian (1998-2005).
Biographical Note:
Gerald W. Williams worked for the U.S. Forest Service from 1979 until his retirement in 2005. From 1979 to 1993, he was a sociologist with the Umpqua and Willamette National Forests in Oregon; in 1993-1998, he served as the regional sociologist for the Pacific Northwest Regional Office in Portland; and from 1998 until his retirement in 2005 he was the national historian for the U.S. Forest Service in Washington, D.C. Williams designed and implemented a regional and national history program for the Forest Service which culminated in his appointment as national historian and his authorship of the centennial history of the Forest Service, The USDA Forest Service -- The First Century, in 2000. He has published more than 75 books, chapters, book reviews, and articles and conference papers exploring a variety of historical topics such as the Native American use of fire to manage environments, the Civilian Conservation Corps, and the U.S. Army's Spruce Production Division during World War I.
Williams is a native of Oregon and earned degrees from Southern Oregon University (B.A., Sociology; M.A. General Studies Social Science) and Washington State University (Ph.D., Sociology).
Bohlman, Herman.; Prentiss, A. M. (Arthur M.)
Kansas City Slide Co.; Keystone View Company.; Underwood & Underwood.; United States. Forest Service.; Weister Company.
Lantern slides.
Columbia River Gorge (Or. and Wash.); Hood, Mount (Or.); McKenzie River (Or.)
Birds--Oregon.; Forests and forestry--Northwest, Pacific.; Logging--Northwest, Pacific.; Salmon--Northwest, Pacific.
Oregon; Photographs; Advertising and Marketing; Forestry and Forest Products; Fisheries and Wildlife; Logging
These materials were acquired by the former University Archives and the Special Collections and Archives Research Center in multiple accessions in 2007-2016. They were originally described as a component of the Gerald W. Williams Collection (MSS WilliamsG) and were separated for description as this collection in 2016.
Collection is open for research. Five lantern slides are damaged or in poor condition and have limited researcher access. These items have been digitized and are availalble online.
The core of Gerald Williams' research materials are maintained as the Gerald W. Williams Papers (MSS WilliamsG). Other materials that were collected by Williams have been described as separate collections: Gerald W. Williams Collection of Forestry and Northwest History Publications (MSS WilliamsPubs); Gerald W. Williams Collection on the Civilian Conservation Corps (MSS CCC); Gerald W. Williams Moving Image and Sound Recordings Collection (FV 320); Gerald W. Williams Collection on Smokey Bear (MSS Smokey); Gerald W. Wiliams Prints Collection (MSS WilliamsPrints); Jason S. Elder Forest Service Diary (MSS Elder); C.C. Hall Photograph Album (P 301); J.F. Ford Photographs (P 308); Forest Service Equipment Development Center Photograph Album (P 311); Mount Hood Area Excursion Photograph Album (P 310); and Frank Patterson Photographic Postcards (P 312). The Herman T. Bohlman Photographs (P 202) includes other images made by Bohlman. The Special Collections and Archives Research Center houses many collections that include lantern slides.
The Gerald W. Williams Lantern Slides Collection is arranged in 6 series: 1. Forest Operations and Trees, circa 1900s-1930s; 2. Landscapes and Scenery, circa 1900s-1930s; 3. Wildlife, Plants, and Flowers, circa 1900s-1930s; 4. Advertisements for McKenzie River Area Local Businesses, circa 1920s-1930s; 5. American Military, Government, and War Propaganda, circa 1900s-1930s; and 6. Diagrams, Illustrations, and People, circa 1900s-1930s.
The Gerald W. Williams Lantern Slides Collection consists of lantern slides assembled and acquired by Williams in the course of his work as a Forest Service sociologist and historian and due to his avocational interest in the history of foresty and the Pacific Northwest region. The slides depict forests and forest operations; landscapes and scenery; birds, wildlife, and plants; and salmon fishing. Many of the images are of Oregon landmarks, including the Columbia River Gorge, Crater Lake, and Mount Hood. Of particular note are a set of lantern slides advertising local businesses in the McKenzie River area. All of the images are undated; an approximate date range for the collection was assigned based on the time period when the creation and use of lantern slides was most prevalent.
Many of the slides are in color. Five of the items are damaged or in poor condition and have been segregated from the builk of the collection. These items have been digitized and are available online.
The collection includes lantern slides by many photographers and producers including the U.S. Forest Service, the Keystone View Company, Arthur M. Prentiss, Underwood and Underwood, Weister Co., Herman T. Bohlman, and the Kansas City Slide Company.
- Forest Operations and Trees, circa 1900s-1930s; Series 1
  Series 1 consists of 29 lantern slides depicting trees, forests, logging, and milling operations.
  - Splash Dam Middle Fork of Little River (Box-item 1.01)
    Slide number: 14039
  - Cutting Small Branches From Fell Spruce (Box-item 1.02)
    Photographer: Bickmore. Slide number: 5524
  - Fir Reproduction from Old Cuttings (Box-item 1.03)
    Slide number: 59461
  - Art Blakely Saw Mill (Box-item 1.04)
    Photographer: Pinchot. Slide number: 936
  - Hauling Logs by Mule Team (Box-item 1.05)
    Photographer: Block. Slide number: 40093
  - Clearing in Potato Field. 5 Miles Below Hot Springs (Box-item 1.06)
    Slide number: 831
  - General Forest (Box-item 1.07)
    Photographer: Lindsey. Slide number: 12336
  - Defective Old Chestnut, in Chestnut Coppice (Box-item 1.08)
    Photographer: Foley. Slide number: 20310
  - Logging Equipment in the Forest (Box-item 1.09)
    Slide number: 1386
  - Monterey Cypress; Man near an Orchard (Box-item 1.10)
    Photographer: Gaskill. Slide number: 4832
  - In a Virgin Douglas Fir Forest (Box-item 1.11)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Slide number: 95451
  - Yellow Pine (Box-item 1.12)
    Slide number: 40019
  - Terror of 50 Year Old White Pine Nation (Box-item 1.13)
    Photographer: Kempton. Slide number: 35798
  - Hauling Logs by Steel Cable (Box-item 1.14)
    Photographer: Plummer. Slide number: 27594
  - Great Trees in the Northwest, Showing a Method of Felling (Box-item 1.15)
    Source: Keystone View Company. Slide number: 29234
  - Regulation Ax (Box-item 1.16)
    Photographer: Pinchot. Slide number: 33794
  - A Forest Destroyed by Fire in Three hours (Box-item 1.17)
    Source: Keystone View Company. Slide number: 22198
  - Successful Seed Felling in India; Longleaf Pine Forest (Box-item 1.18)
    Photographer: Cleadow. Slide number: 8353
  - Tree Generations of Chestnut (Box-item 1.19)
    Photographer: Zon. Slide number: 28975
  - Tulip Tree Sprouts (Box-item 1.20)
    Photographer: Foley. Slide number: 20312
  - Lodgepole Pines (Box-item 1.21)
  - Tulip Tree 54" On Stump (Box-item 1.22)
    Slide number: 1319
  - Mill of the Union Lumber Company (Box-item 1.23)
    Photographer: Fisher. Slide number: 4187
  - Tulip-Poplar Peeled for Pulp (Box-item 1.24)
  - Western Hemlock Roots on Fallen Douglas Spruce Exposed by Fire (Box-item 1.25)
  - Sugar Pine (Box-item 1.26)
  - Young Mandan Belt (6 Years Old); Irrigated Garden Keeps Dust Out of the House on Farm of M.J. Campbell (Box-item 3.01)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service
    Location: Denton, Montana. Slide number: 291045. Notes: Slide is cracked. Image is available online.
  - Rolling a Log onto the Timber Slide (Box-item 3.02)
    Slide number: 2026. Note: Slide is cracked. Image is available online.
  - Forest Ranger and his Family (Box-item 3.03)
    Location: Northern California
    Slide number: 31. Note: Slide is cracked. Image is available online.
- Landscapes and Scenery, circa 1900s-1930s; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of 56 lantern slides depicting landscapes and scenery. Many of the images are of Oregon landmarks including the Columbia River Gorge, Mount Hood, and Crater Lake.
  - The Pinnacles (200 ft.) (Box-item 1.27)
    Perhaps at Crater Lake.
  - "Sacajawea and Jean-Baptiste" statue in Washington Park (Box-item 1.28)
    Location: Portland, Oregon
  - "Coming of the White Man" statue in Washington Park (Box-item 1.29)
  - Riding Trail (Box-item 1.30)
    Photographer: Arthur M. Prentiss
    Slide number: 32973
  - Roundabout by the Beach (Box-item 1.31)
  - Aerial View of a City (Box-item 1.32)
  - River Scene (Box-item 1.33)
  - River Scene (Box-item 1.34)
  - River Scene (Box-item 1.35)
  - Herd of Sheep (Box-item 1.36)
  - Herd of Sheep (Box-item 1.37)
  - Bridal Veil Falls (Box-item 1.38)
  - Yellow Pine (Box-item 1.39)
    Location: Central Oregon
  - Wau-kee-na Falls (Box-item 1.40)
  - Looking up River from Crown Point (Box-item 1.41)
  - Tumwater Falls at Celilo (Box-item 1.42)
  - Heron Rookery toward Linnton Skyline Road (Box-item 1.43)
  - A Perfect Reflection (Box-item 1.44)
    Location: Crater Lake
  - Andesite Zigzag Mountains (Box-item 1.45)
  - Mount Hood near Phlox Point (Box-item 1.46)
  - Mount Hood (Box-item 1.47)
  - Three Arch Rocks (Box-item 1.48)
    Location: Oceanside, Oregon
  - Multnomah Falls (670 ft. and 80 ft.) (Box-item 1.49)
    Slide number: 12
  - River Scene (Box-item 1.50)
  - Highway - Castle Rock in Distance (Box-item 1.51)
    Slide number: 20
  - St. Peters Dome (Box-item 1.52)
  - Mt. Hood at a Distance (Box-item 1.53)
  - Basaltic Column (Box-item 1.54)
    Slide number: 8
  - Sheperd's Dell (Box-item 1.55)
  - Sunset on the Columbia River (Box-item 1.56)
  - Icicles over 100 Feet at Multnomah Falls (Box-item 1.57)
  - Andesite Zig Zag Mountains (Box-item 1.58)
  - Phlox at Mt. Hood (Box-item 1.59)
  - Multnomah Falls (Box-item 1.60)
  - Cascade Locks (Box-item 1.61)
    Slide number: 13
  - Horsetail Falls (Box-item 1.62)
  - McKenzie River Highway 1920s (Box-item 1.63)
  - Sheep Grazing on Point of Ridge, Lower Portion of Rincon la Josa National Forest (Box-item 1.64)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Slide number: 910828.
  - Yucca mohavensis (Box-item 1.65)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Location: Kingman, Arizona. Slide number: 392562.
  - Entrance to the Sacramento Municipal Camp Ground at Sayles Flat, El Dorado National Forest (Box-item 1.66)
    Source: School of Forestry, Moscow, Idaho. Slide number: 158146
  - Petrified Forest (Box-item 1.67)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood, N.Y. Location: Arizona. Slide number: 6148.
  - The Natural Bridge (Box-item 1.68)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood. Location: Rockbridge, Co. Slide number: 5656.
  - Marshall Pass (10,856 ft.) Continental Divide (Box-item 1.69)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood. Location: SE to Mt. Antero, Colorado. Slide number: 10631.
  - Sunset at Lake St, Mary in Glacier National Park (Box-item 1.70)
  - Beaver Dam in Estes Park, Colorado (Box-item 1.71)
  - Cottages at Municipal Camp, Land Leased by the City of Los Angeles from the Forest Service (Box-item 1.72)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Location: Angeles National Forest. Slide number: 33376A.
  - Mountain (Box-item 1.73)
  - Forest Scene (Box-item 1.74)
  - Forest Scene (Box-item 1.75)
  - Cactus Scene (Box-item 1.76)
  - Mountains (Box-item 1.77)
    Publisher: Riley Optical Inst. Co. Inc. Location: British Columbia, Canada. Slide number: 14647.
  - Farm Equipment being Pulled by Horses (Box-item 1.78)
    Slide number: 31
  - Logs Loaded onto Railroad Cars (Box-item 1.79)
    Slide number: 11
  - Seining Chinook Salmon (Box-item 1.80)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood. Location: Columbia River, Oregon. Slide number: 6236.
  - Thumb Needle Basaltic Column (Box-item 3.04)
    Perhaps in the Columbia River Gorge. Note: Cracked slide. Image is available online.
  - Mt. Adams from Mt. Rainier (Box-item 3.05)
    Publisher: Putnam and Valentine Photo. Note: Cracked slide. Image is available online.
- Wildlife, Plants, and Flowers, circa 1900s-1930s; Series 3
  Series 3 consists of 45 lantern slides of birds, plants and wildlife. Several of the bird photographs were taken at Malheur or Klamath. Also of note are several images made by Herman T. Bohlman. This series also includes portrait photographs of naturalists and group photographs of individuals on nature trips.
  - Black Crowned Night Heron (Box-item 1.81)
    Publisher: Weister Co.Slide Number: 54.
  - Forster's Tern (Box-item 1.82)
    Slide number: 30
  - Blue Heron (Box-item 1.83)
    Slide number: 53
  - Pelican (Box-folder 1.84)
    Slide number: 78
  - Blue Heron (Box-folder 1.85)
    Slide number: 52
  - Pelicans (Box-folder 1.86)
    Slide number: 80
  - Red-tailed Hawk (Box-folder 1.87)
    Photographer: H.T. Bohlman
  - Caspain Tern (Box-item 1.88)
    Photographer; H.T. Bohlman. Slide number: 74.
  - Unidentified Black and White Bird (Box-item 1.89)
    Slide number: 34
  - Seagull (Box-item 1.90)
    Slide number: 60
  - Cormorant (Box-item 1.91)
    Slide number: 33
  - Western Grebe (Box-item 1.92)
  - Pelican (Box-item 1.93)
    Slide number: 93
  - White Faced Ibis (Box-item 1.94)
    Slide number: 48
  - Frog and Dead Bird (Box-item 1.95)
  - Unidentified Birds (Box-item 2.01)
  - Unidentified Bird (Box-item 2.02)
  - California Kingsnake (Box-item 2.03)
  - Scenery with Small Unidentified Birds in Foreground (Box-item 2.04)
  - Kingsnake (Box-item 2.05)
  - Hawk (Box-item 2.06)
  - Unidentified Bird (Box-item 2.07)
  - California Kingsnake (Box-item 2.08)
  - Kingsnake (Box-item 2.09)
  - Frog and Dead Bird (Box-item 2.10)
  - Ruffled Grouse (Box-item 2.11)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Location: Northwestern Admiralty Island, Alaska. Slide number: 393363.
  - Mearns Quail near Fresco River (Box-item 2.12)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Slide number: 26312A.
  - Quail on a Nest (Box-item 2.13)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Location: Essex, Iowa. Slide number: X225.
  - Young Girl Holding Snakes (Box-item 2.14)
  - Unidentified Wild Cat (Box-item 2.15)
  - Unidentified Wild Cat (Box-item 2.16)
  - Young Girl Holding Snakes (Box-item 2.17)
  - Ducks on a Beach (Box-item 2.18)
  - Dr. Louis F. Henderson Portrait (Box-item 2.19)
  - Dr. Louis F. Henderson Portrait (Box-item 2.20)
  - Dr. Menzies Portrait (Box-item 2.21)
  - Dr. Menzies Portrait (Box-item 2.22)
  - Group Photo Outdoors (Box-item 2.23)
  - Audubon Headquarters (Box-item 2.24)
  - William S. Raker and Martin Gorman, Botanist (Box-item 2.25)
  - Oregon Audubon Flower Trip (Box-item 2.26)
  - Unnamed Plants and Berries (Box-item 2.27)
  - Rydberg Clover. Trifolium rydberg (Box-item 2.28)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. Slide number: X408.
  - Unnamed Flowering Plant (Box-item 2.29)
    Photographer: Sowell-Simon Studio
  - Unnamed Flowering Plant (Box-item 2.30)
- Advertisements for McKenzie River Area Local Businesses, circa 1920s-1930s; Series 4
  Series 4 consists of advertisements published by the Kansas City Slide Co. These were stock slides that had been customized for local businesses and were likely used during intermissions at movie theaters. The series includes 26 lantern slides.
  - Advertisement for L.A. Romberg Plumbing (Box-item 2.31)
    Location: McKenzie Bridge
  - Advertisement for Blue McKenzie Lodge (Box-item 2.32)
  - Advertisement for Riverview Lodge (Box-item 2.33)
    Location: McKenzie
  - Advertisement for Lauer's McKenzie Bridge (Box-item 2.34)
  - Advertisement for Bob's Cabinet Shop (Box-item 2.35)
    Location: Leaburg, Oregon
  - Advertisement for Tommy's Gateway Service (Box-item 2.36)
    Location: Blue River, Oregon
  - Advertisement for Reg. & Faye Taylor Proprietors (Box-item 2.37)
  - Advertisement for Phil's Phine Phoods (Box-item 2.38)
  - Advertisement for J. C. Wycoff Garage (Box-item 2.39)
  - Advertisement for Bob's Cabinet Shop (Box-item 2.40)
  - Advertisement for Helen's Hobby Hut (Box-item 2.41)
  - Advertisement for W & S Fuel Co. (Box-item 2.42)
  - Advertisement for Lucille's Shell Work (Box-item 2.43)
    Location: Vida, Oregon
  - Advertisement for Bob Richardson Cabinet Work (Box-item 2.44)
    Location: McKenzie Bridge, Oregon
  - Advertisement for Osborn's Lockers (Box-item 2.45)
  - Advertisement for Frankys McKenzie Village Café (Box-item 2.46)
  - Advertisement for Glen H. Horne Fire Insurance (Box-item 2.47)
  - Advertisement for Osborn's Food Lockers (Box-item 2.48)
  - Advertisement for Blue River Theatre (Box-item 2.49)
  - Advertisement for Leaburg Cafe (Box-item 2.50)
  - Advertisement for Cascade Resort (Box-item 2.51)
  - Advertisement for Belknap Springs (Box-item 2.52)
  - Advertisement for Blue River Automotive and Machine Co. (Box-item 2.53)
  - Advertisement for Keller's Store (Box-item 2.54)
  - Advertisement for Blue River Body and Fender Shop (Box-item 2.55)
  - Advertisement for C.D. Sikes, Stainless Steel Dealer (Box-item 2.56)
    Location: Finn Rock, Oregon
- American Military, Government, and War Propaganda, circa 1900s-1930s; Series 5
  Series 5 consists of 15 lantern slides depicting landmark federal buildings in Washington, D.C.; war-time advertisements; and German ships.
  - Union Troops Returning (Box-item 2.57)
    Source: Education Museum
  - U.S. Money Being Printed - Bureau of Engraving (Box-item 2.58)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood. Location: Washington D.C. Slide number: 140-11146.
  - Congressional Library (Box-item 2.59)
    Publisher: Keystone View Co. Factories. Location: Washington D.C. Slide number: 95.
  - White House (Box-item 2.60)
  - Supreme Court Room (Box-item 2.61)
    Location: Washington D.C. Slide number: 89.
  - Advertisement for War Stamps (Box-item 2.62)
  - Capitol Senate Chamber (Box-item 2.63)
    Publisher: Keystone View Co. Factories. Location: Washington D.C.
  - U.S. Food Administration Advertisement for Saving Food During Wartime (Box-item 2.64)
    Publisher: Novelty Slide Co.
  - Snow for Water Supply - Belgica Antarctic Expedition (Box-item 2.65)
    Publisher: Keystone View Co. Factories. Slide number: 344
  - Windward and Eric-Peary Expedition to Greenland, 1901 (Box-item 2.66)
    Publisher: Keystone View Co. Factories. Slide number: 342.
  - German Ship (Box-item 2.67)
  - German Ship (Box-item 2.68)
  - German Ship (Box-item 2.69)
  - German Ship (Box-item 2.70)
  - German Ship (Box-item 2.71)
- Diagrams, Illustrations, and People, circa 1900s-1930s; Series 6
  Series 6 consists of 13 lantern slides of various topics that may have been used for teaching or entertainment. Of special note is an image of salmon fishing on Puget Sound.
  - Seal of the State of Oregon (Box-item 2.72)
  - YMCA Camp Group Photograph (Box-item 2.73)
    Location: Detroit, Oregon
  - Article entitled "How the Horse Has Grown in 6 Million Years" (Box-item 2.74)
  - Slide with Bird Beak and Talon Types (Box-item 2.75)
  - Bird Diagram (Box-item 2.76)
  - Group of College Girls in Caverns (Box-item 2.77)
    Source: U.S. Forest Service. L ocation: New Market, Virginia, on Highway U.S. No. 11. Slide number: 338756.
  - Poem with Illustration (Box-item 2.78)
    Publisher: Quality Slide Co. Slide number: 2.
  - Poem with Illustration (Box-item 2.79)
    Publisher: Quality Slide Co. Slide number: 3.
  - Hudson's Bay Company Crest (Box-item 2.80)
  - Neath Old Cherry Tree (Box-item 2.81)
    Artist: Scott and Van Atlena. Slide number: 3.
  - Couple Sitting in Nature (Box-item 2.82)
    Artist: Scott and Van Atlena
  - Brailing-Taking Salmon from the Trap (Box-item 2.83)
    Publisher: Underwood & Underwood. Location: Puget Sound. Slide number: 6229.
  - Cutting Snow Blocks for Igloo (Box-item 2.84)
    Source: Educational Museum. Slide number: 1080.